Leonard Volk Collection
Leonard Volk Collection
1845-1957
Volk, Leonard Wells, 1828-1895.
71 items.
Papers of the American sculptor. Correspondence to and from Volk family members; photographs of a bust of Volk by David Richards, works by Volk, family members, and the areas around Pittsfield, Massachusetts and Wells, New York; and material relating to the acquisition of the collection by Edward Deming Andrews, grand-nephew of Volk.
148722
Biographical History
Leonard Wells Volk (1828-1895) was an American sculptor. Born November 7, 1828 in Wellstown (now Wells), New York, he was one of twelve children of Garrett and Elizabeth Gesner Volk. At sixteen he began work as a marble cutter in his father's shop in Pittsfield, Massachusetts. Four years later, in 1848, he went to St. Louis, Missouri, where he opened a studio and studied drawing and modeling independent of formal instruction. Stephen A. Douglas, a cousin of Volk's wife, became interested in his work, and in 1858 supplied funds for Volk to study art in Rome. Returning to the United States in 1867, Volk settled in Chicago, where he founded the Chicago Academy of Design and served as its president for eight years.
Among Volk's principal works are the Douglas Monument (Chicago), the Soldiers' and Sailors' Monument (Rochester, N.Y.), and statues of Abraham Lincoln, Stephen A. Douglas, General James G. Shields, Elihu B. Washburne, Zachariah Chandler, and David Davis. In 1860 he created a life mask of President Lincoln, one of only two ever made, as well as plaster casts of Lincoln's hands.
Volk was married to Emily Clarissa Barlow of Bethany, New York in 1852; they had a son, Douglas, who became a figure and portrait painter, and daughter.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Leonard Volk Collection consists of correspondence, photographs, and material relating to the creation of the collection by Mr. and Mrs. Edward Deming Andrews.
Correspondence consists of original letters between Volk and his family. All are personal letters and refer to events and people of the time, such as President Lincoln, the Civil War, and the death of Stephen A. Douglas.
Photographs include those of a bust of Volk by David Richards, Volk's sculpture for the Stephen A. Douglas monument and his bust of Judge Knickerbocker, friends and relatives, and the areas around Pittsfield, Massachusetts and Wells, New York.
The Mr. and Mrs. Edward Deming Andrews material contains Leonard Volk biographical material and correspondence relating to their acquisition and donation of the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
All material is arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Civil War (U.S.); Volk, Leonard Wells, 1828-1895.; Volk family.; Art, American.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 19th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Artists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Edward Deming Andrews, 1968.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing
    - 1858-1888 (Box 1)
  - Of others
    - Abram Volk (brother), 1845-1869 (Box 1)
    - Carrie Volk, 1880 (Box 1)
    - E. Volk, 1880-1881 (Box 1)
    - Emily Volk (wife), 1858 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Bust of Volk, 1884 (Box 1)
  - Sculpture by Volk (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous people and places, 1885-1892 (Box 1)
- Mr. and Mrs. Edward Deming Andrews material
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1)